short rest.
They did not sing or tell stories that day, even though the weather improved,
nor the next day, nor the day after.
They had begun to feel that danger was not far away on either side. They camped
under the stars, and their horses had more to eat than they had, for there was
plenty of grass, but there was not much in their bags, even with what they had
got from the trolls. One morning they forded a river at a wide, shallow place
full of the noise of stones and foam.
The far bank was steep and slippery.
When they got to the top of it, leading their ponies, they saw that the great
mountains had marched down very near to them. Already they seemed only a day's
easy journey from the feet of the nearest. Dark and dre it looked, though
there were patches of sunlight on its brown sides, and behind its shoulders
the tips of snow peaks gleamed. Is that the mountain?" asked Bilbo, in a solemn
voice, looking at it with round eyes. He had never seen a thing that looked so big before.
Of course not, said Balon. That is only the beginning of the Misty Mountains,
and we have got to get through, or over or under those somehow, before we can
come into Wilderland beyond, and it is a deal of a way, even from the other side
of them to the lonely mountain in the east, where Smile lies on our treasure.
"Oh," said Bilbo, and just at that moment he felt more tired than he ever
remembered feeling before. He was thinking once again of his comfortable
chair before the fire in his favorite sitting room in his hobbit hole, and of
the kettle singing. Not for the last time. Now Gandalf led the way. We must
not miss the road, or we shall be done for, he said. We need food for one
thing, and rest in reasonable safety.
Also, it is very necessary to tackle the Misty Mountains by the proper path, or
else you will get lost in them, and have to come back and start at the beginning
again, if you ever get back at all."
They asked him where he was making for, and he answered, "You are come to the
very edge of the wild, as some of you may know. Hidden somewhere ahead of us
is the fair valley of Rivendell, where Elron lives in the last homely house. I
sent a message by my friends and we are expected.
That sounded nice and comforting, but they had not got there yet, and it was
not so easy as it sounds to find the last homely house west of the mountains.
There seemed to be no trees and no valleys and no hills to break the ground
in front of them. Only one vast slope going slowly up and up to meet the feet
of the nearest mountain. a wide land the color of heather and crumbling rock with
patches and slashes of grass green and moss green showing where water might be.
Morning passed, afternoon came, but in all the silent waste there was no sign
of any dwelling. They were growing anxious, for they saw now that the house
might be hidden almost anywhere between them and the mountains. They came on
unexpected valleys narrow with steep sides that opened suddenly at their
feet, and they looked down surprised to see trees below them and running water
at the bottom. There were gullies that they could almost leap over, but very
deep with waterfalls in them. There were dark ravines that one could neither jump
over nor climb into. There were bogs, some of them green, pleasant places to
look at, with flowers growing bright and tall. But a pony that walked there with
a pack on its back would never have come out again. It was indeed a much wider
land from the ford to the mountains than ever you would have guessed. Bilbo was
astonished. The only path was marked with white stones, some of which were
small, and others were half covered with moss or heather. Altogether it was a
very slow business following the track, even guided by Gandalf, who seemed to
know his way about pretty well. His head and beard wag this way and that as he
looked for the stones, and they followed his lead, but they seemed no nearer to
the end of the search, when the day began to fail. Tea time had long gone
by, and it seemed supper time would soon do the same. There were moths fluttering
about, and the light became very dim, for the moon had not risen. Bilbo's poly
began to stumble over roots and stones.
They came to the edge of a steep fall on the ground so suddenly that Gandalf's
horse nearly slipped down the slope.
"Here it is at last," he called, and the others gathered round him and looked
over the edge. They saw a valley far below. They could hear the voice of
hurrying water in a rocky bed at the bottom. The scent of trees was in the
air, and there was a light on the valley side across the water.
Bilbo never forgot the way they slithered and slipped in the dusk down
the steep zigzag path into the secret valley of Rivendell.
The air grew warmer as they got lower, and the smell of the pine trees made him
drowsy, so that every now and again he nodded and nearly fell off or bumped his
nose on the pony's neck. Their spirits rose as they went down and down. The
trees changed to beach and oak, and there was a comfortable feeling in the
twilight. The last green had almost faded out of the grass when they came at
length to an open glade not far above the banks of the stream.
It smels like elves, thought Bilbo, and he looked up at the stars. They were
burning bright and blue.
Just then there came a burst of song like laughter in the trees.
An what are you doing and where are you going? Your ponies need shoeing. The
river is flowing. Oh, tra la la la la la
la la la la la la la la la la la la la
la la la la la la la la la here down in the valley.
Oh, what are you seeking? And where are you making? The are wreaking,
the banics are baking. Oh, trill li. The valley is jolly. Haha.
On.
Where are you going? with beards or a wagging. No knowing, no knowing what
brings Mr. Baggins and Balon and Dwallan and Duallin down into the valley in
June. Ha! Oh, will you be staying or will you be flying? Your ponies are
straying. The daylight is dying. To fly would be folly. To stay would be jolly
and listen and hark till the end of the dark to our tune. Haha. So they laughed
and sang in the trees, and pretty fair nonsense, I dare say you think it. Not
that they would care. They would only laugh all the more if he told them so.
They were elves, of course. Soon Bilbo caught glimpses of them as the darkness
deepened. He loved elves, though he seldom met them, but he was a little
frightened of them, too.
Dwarves don't get on well with them.
Even decent enough dwarves like Thoren and his friends think them foolish,
which is a very foolish thing to think, or get annoyed with them, for some elves
tease them and laugh at them, and most of all at their beards.
Well, well, said a voice, just look, Bilbo the Hobbit on a pony, my dear, isn't it delicious?
Most astonishing wonderful. Then off they went into another song as
ridiculous as the one I have written down in full. At last one a tall young
fellow came out from the trees and bowed to Gandalf and to Thoren.
Welcome to the valley, he said. Thank you, said Thorin a bit gruffly. But
Gandalf was already off his horse and among the elves talking merrily with
them. You are a little out of your way, said the elf. That is, if you are making
for the only path across the water and to the house beyond, we will set you
right, but you had best get on foot until you are over the bridge. Are you
going to stay a bit and sing with us, or will you go straight on? Supper is
preparing over there, he said. I can smell the woodf fires for the cooking.
Tired as he was, Bilbo would have liked to stay a while. Elvish singing is not a
thing to miss in June under the stars, not if you care for such things. Also,
he would have liked to have a few private words with these people that
seem to know his names and all about him, although he had never seen them
before. He thought their opinion of his adventure might be interesting. Elves
know a lot and are wondrous folk for news and know what is going on among the
peoples of the land as quick as water flows or quicker. But the dwarves were
all for supper as soon as possible just then and would not stay. On they all
went leading their ponies till they were brought to a good path and so at last to
the very brink of the river. It was flowing fast and noisily as mountain
streams do of a summer evening when sun has been all day on the snow far up
above. There was only a narrow bridge of stone without a parapit as narrow as a
poly could well walk on. And over that they had to go slow and careful, one by
one, each leading his poly by the bridal. The elves had brought bright
lanterns to the shore, and they sang a merry song as the party went across.
Don't dip your beard in the foam, father, they cried to Thoren, who was
bent almost onto his hands and knees. It is long enough without watering it. Mind
Bilbo doesn't eat all the cakes, they called. He is too fat to get through
keyholes yet. Hush, hush, good people, and good night, said Gandalf, who came
last. Valleys have ears, and some elves have over merry tongues. Good night. And
so at last they all came to the last homely house and found its doors flung
wide. Now it is a strange thing, but things that are good to have and days
that are good to spend are soon told about and not much to listen to. While
things that are uncomfortable, palpitating, and even gruesome may make
a good tale and take a deal of telling anyway. They stayed long in that good
house, 14 days at least, and they found it hard to leave. Bilbo would gladly
have stopped there forever and ever, even supposing a wish would have taken
him right back to his hobbit hole without trouble. Yet there is little to
tell about their stay. The master of the house was an elf friend, one of those
people whose fathers came into the strange stories before the beginning of
history. the wars of the evil goblins and the elves and the first men in the
north. In those days of our tale, there were still some people who had both
elves and heroes of the north for ancestors. And Elron, the master of the
house was their chief. He was as noble and as fair in face as an elf lord, as
strong as a warrior, as wise as a wizard, as venerable as a king of
dwarves, and as kind as summer. He comes into many tales, but his part in the
story of Bilbo's great adventure is only a small one, though important, as you
will see, if we ever get to the end of it. His house was perfect, whether he
liked food or sleep, or work, or storytelling, or singing, or just
sitting and thinking best, or a pleasant mixture of them all. Evil things did not
come into that valley. I wish I had time
to tell you even a few of the tales or
one or two of the songs that they heard in that house. All of them, the ponies
as well, grew refreshed and strong in a few days there. Their clothes were
mended as well as their bruises, their tempers and their hopes. Their bags were
filled with food and provisions light to carry but strong to bring them over the
mountain passes. Their plans were improved with the best advice. So the
time came to midsummer eve, and they were to go on again with the early sun
on midsummer morning. Elron knew all about runes of every kind. That day he
looked at the swords they had brought from the trolls lair, and he said,
"These are not troll make. They are old swords, very old swords of the high
elves of the west, my kin. They were made in Gondolind for the goblin wars.
They must have come from a dragon's horde or goblin plunder for dragons and
goblins destroyed that city many ages ago. This Thoren, the run's name
Orcrest, the goblin cleaver in the ancient tongue of Gondolan. It was a
famous blade. This Gandalf was glaming faux hammer that the king of Gondolan
once wore. Keep them well. Whence did the trolls get them, I wonder, said
Thoren, looking at his sword with new interest.
I could not say," said Eland, "but one may guess that your trolls had plundered
other plunders, or come on the remnants of old robberies in some hold in the
mountains. I have heard that there are still forgotten treasures of old to be
found in the deserted caverns of the mines of Moria since the dwarf and
goblin war." Thorin pondered these words. "I will keep this sword in
honor," he said. "May it soon cleave goblins once again." A wish that is
likely to be granted soon enough in the mountains, said Eland. But show me now
your map. He took it and gazed long at
it, and he shook his head, for if he did not altogether approve of dwarves and
their love of gold, he hated dragons and their cruel wickedness, and he grieved
to remember the ruin of the town of Dale and its merry bells, and the burned
banks of the bright river running. The moon was shining in a broad silver
crescent. He held up the map and the white light shone through it. "What is
this?" he said. "There are moon letters here beside the plain runes which say 5
ft hide the door and three may walk a breast." "What are moon letters?" asked
the hobbit, full of excitement. He loved maps, as I have told you before, and he
also liked runes and letters and cunning handwriting, though when he wrote
himself it was a bit thin and spidery.
Moon letters are rune letters, but you cannot see them, said Eland. Not when
you look straight at them. They can only be seen when the moon shines behind
them, and what is more, with the more cunning sort, it must be a moon of the
same shape and season as the day when they were written. The dwarves invented
them, and wrote them with silver pens, as your friends could tell you. These
must have been written on a midsummer's eve in a crescent moon a long while ago.
What do they say?" asked Gandalf and Thorin together. A bit vexed perhaps,
that even Elrron should have found this out first, though really there had not
been a chance before, and there would not have been another until goodness
knows when. Stand by the Greystone when the thrush knocks, read Eland, and the
setting sun with the last light of Duran's day will shine upon the keyhole.
Durin. Duran said Thorin. He was the father of the fathers of the eldest race
of dwarves, the long beards, and my first ancestor. I am his heir. Then what
is Duran's day? asked Eland. The first day of the dwarf's new year, said
Thorin. Is as all should know, the first day of the last moon of autumn on the
threshold of winter. We still call it Durham's day when the last moon of
autumn and the sun are in the sky together. But this will not help us
much, I fear, for it passes our skill in these days to guess when such a time
will come again. That remains to be seen, said Gandalf. Is there any more
writing? None to be seen by this moon, said Aland, and he gave the map back to
Thoren. And then they went down to the water to see the elves dance and sing
upon the midsummer's eve. The next morning was a midsummer's morning, as
fair and fresh as could be dreamed, blue sky and never a cloud, and the sun
dancing on the water. Now they rode away amid songs of farewell and good speed,
with their hearts ready for more adventure, and with a knowledge of the
road they must follow over the misty mountains to the land beyond. Chapter 4.